<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Expedient for peace perswading an agreement amongst Christians &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08740716</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08740716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41719</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41719)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1259:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Expedient for peace perswading an agreement amongst Christians &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41719:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Expedient for Peace: PERSWADING An Agreement amongſt CHRISTIANS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I Saw the World in a Flame, and among the reſt, have thrown in my Bucket to quench it: Indeed I have been ſomething in haſte; but where there is Fire in the caſe, this muſt not be called a Fault, but a Duty: But I hope I have not made ſo much haſte, or been ſo ill guided, as to miſtake with ſome, and to fill my Bucket with Oyl inſtead of Water. I'll aſſure thee I drew it from a very Charitable Fountain, and am none of thoſe that have either Reſpect to Perſons or Parties: But I think I need not make my Excuſe for the enſuing Diſcourſe, for that would be to Apologize for doing my Duty. All that I ſhall deſire of thee is, That before thou begin to read, thou lay aſide all thoſe Common Enemies to Truth and Peace,</hi> viz. <hi>Paſſion, Prejudice, Partiality,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or elſe we ſhall both of us loſe our Labours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>RELIGION (I will not ſay the True Religion) as men manage it, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the grievance and burden of the Nation, and is the proper Province of the State to take it into conſideration: When the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was born, the Holy Angels An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them was, <hi>Glory to God in the Higheſt, Peace on Earth, Good Will towards Men;</hi> but ill men, and the Devil together, have ordered things ſo, that the ſame is inverted, and may now be ſaid, <hi>D. ſhonour to God on High, Confuſion on Earth, Ill Will towards Men:</hi> The truth is, men have been ſo madly extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagant, in the things they call Religion, and have made ſuch tumults and ſtirs in this World about the things of another, that notwithſtanding I contend earneſtly for a Toleration, as the only remedy to heal them, yet 'tis not for a Toleration to do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; and I can willingly ſubſcribe, after all I ſhall ſay in behalf thereof, that no ſort or party of men ſhould be indulged in any of their Religions or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, of what denomination ſoever, but thoſe that are ready and willing to give the State ſecurity for their Good Behaviour, and Peaceable Living. Now the concern of Religion is to make men hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py here, as well as hereafter; and after all men's talk, has but two Parts, <hi>To love the Lord our God with all our Hearts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And our Neighbour as our ſelves:</hi> But men have been ſo mad, that they have almoſt vacated both, by over zealouſly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreetly endeavouring to perform the firſt; and have thought they could not love God enough, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they hated and deſtroyed their Neighbour: That theſe things are but too true, all Chriſtendom by ſad Experience can atteſt, and in particular, this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Nation; which like a Ship at Sea, has been long a ſinking<hi>:</hi> The Captain indeed labours to ſave her, having found out her leaks, and call to his men for affiſtance; but they like madmen, every one endeavour to ſecure ſomething of her Cargoe, not conſidering that when the Ship is gone, all is gone; and inſtead of aſſiſting, do unreaſonably oppoſe him: So that he muſt ſave them againſt their Wills, or they will inevitably periſh.</p>
            <p>Indeed it is a lamentable thing to conſider, that that ſame Religion which was given by Heaven on purpoſe to the Sons of Men to make them happy, ſhould by an unhappy concurrence of evil Accidents, make them miſerable; and I think to find out thoſe evil Accidents, 'tis the duty of every Man, eſpecially of every Chriſtian; and therefore I will lay down my Obſervations thereof, altho' I meet with the common fate of Reconcllers, to have blows for my pains.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41719:2"/>
Then Firſt, I take notice men make a falſe Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of the Differences and Diſſentions of men in points of Religion, and call them criminal, when they are not; and endeavour to reconcile them, when 'tis impoſſible; and put too great a value on Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that is, when men do the ſame things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; not regarding ſo much, the Truth, Unity and Sincerity of their Minds, as the Company, Preſence and Congregation of their Bodies in one Place, and performing a thing after the ſame manner.</p>
            <p>All the World will acknowledge with me, that what is impoſſible to be done, is not neceſſary to be done. Now as long as men have variety of Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſeveral Educations, Conſtitutions, Tempers, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, Hopes, Fears, Degrees of Light, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Underſtanding, ſeveral Capacities, Offices and Imployments; 'tis impoſſible, (and therefore not neceſſary) they ſhould be all of one Mind<hi>:</hi> And therefore he that attempts it, does like him that claps his Shoulder to the Ground to ſtop an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake; that would ſtop the courſe of the Sun, ſtem the raging Ocean, or pull down the Pillars of the Earth; 'Tis fooliſh therefore to wiſh it or expect it, and they that endeavour it, do but vex and trouble the World; and thinking to procure, they but ſpoil all its Harmony, which conſiſts in ſo great variety of Diſcords.</p>
            <p>It has been ſaid by a learned Prelate, that in the large interval of ſixteen hundred and odd years, ſo much juggling hath paſſed in Chriſtendom, <hi>That the Obſcurity of ſome Queſtions, the nicety of ſome Articles, the intricacy of ſome Revelations, the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Humane <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, the windings of Logick, the tricks of Adverſaries, the ſubtilty of Sophiſters, the ingagement of Educations, perſonal Affections, the portentous number of Writers, the infinity of Authorities, the vaſtneſs of ſome Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as conſiſting in the Enumeration of many Particulars, the uncertainty of others, the ſeveral degrees of Probabilities, the difficulty of Scriptures, the invalidity of Probation of Tradition, the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of all exterior Arguments to each other, and their open Conteſtation, the publick violence done to Authors and Records, the private Arts and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantings, the falſifyings and ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fatigable Induſtry of ſome to abuſe all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings, and all Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions into their own Opinions: Theſe and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand more, even all the difficulties of Things, all the weakneſſes of Man, and all the Arts of the Devil, have made it impoſſible for any man in ſo great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of matter not to be</hi> deceiv'd; And ſay I too, have made it equally impoſſible for men to <hi>agree,</hi> or be all of <hi>One Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been made plainly appear, that Rites and Ceremonies, that ſuch and ſuch Veſtments, ſuch and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Miniſters ſuch Diſcipline, Gevern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or way of Adminiſtration, ſuch Places or Times, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are things of an <hi>indifferent</hi> Nature, and not of abſolute <hi>Neceſſity</hi> to Men's Salvation, nor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Being or Eſſence of God's Church; but are things alterable according to Contingencies and Emergencies, to be retained or diſallowed, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the cuſtom of Places or Nations, or as they are made plainly to appear to miniſter to the Ends of Peace and Charity, for the Edification of God's Church, and not Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And that the eſſential and fundamental qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that make a man a Chriſtian, and a true Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Jeſus Chriſt, are Holineſs, Purity, Piety, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Belief in God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and our Warrant herein, is what St. <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Romans, This is the Word of Faith which we Preach, That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus Christ, and believe with thine Heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved;</hi> as alſo St. <hi>John, For every Spirit that confeſſes that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God; God dwelleth in him, and he in God:</hi> So that ſuch a belief, with ſincere and hearty endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to pleaſe God according to the beſt Notices a man can get, will ſecure a man his Salvation; if it will not, there is no Salvation to be had at all.</p>
            <p>Now the beſt Notices we can get, and only Rule to direct our Lives and Actions, are the Books of the Old and New Teſtament, wherein are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Tranſactions of Heaven with the Sons of Men, and are of an ineſtimable value, teaching all things fully that relate to God or Men, as to the Nature and Worſhip of the one, or the Duty and Salvation of the other. Now that men can under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand theſe Books, is a thing without all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; (and only diſputed by them whoſe intereſt it is they ſhould not,) I mean men of ordinary and mean Capacities; for if not, to what end were they wrote? Or why to them directed? And why are all commanded to read and ſearch them, if they were not capable to underſtand them? And how can ſuch men who deny it, be able to vindicate the Wiſdom, Goodneſs, or Juſtice of Almighty God, in deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Creatures a Rule to walk by, and exact a due conformity thereto, if they were not capable to underſtand it? No certainly, the Good God, as he has condeſcended to give his Creatures a Rule, ſo he has calculated this Rule to all their Capacities, and ſo adapted the one for the other, that they have the greateſt reaſon in the World to Adore and Admire his Wiſdom and Goodneſs for the ſame.</p>
            <p>I will allow that ſome can better underſtand them than others, and that they are not equally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood of all, becauſe of the difference of men's Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities and Acquirements, and becauſe they ſhould have a dependance, and be beholding to one another,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41719:2"/>
which miniſters to Charity; but then nothing is more certain than that all men of the <hi>meaneſt</hi> Capacities, may underſtand them ſufficient, and enough for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, if they come with a ſincere affection of being inſtructed, and of finding out Truth; otherwiſe they would not anſwer the end for which they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned: Some things indeed the deepeſt Heads can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach, and others, the weakeſt Underſtandings can hardly poſſibly miſtake, and thoſe too, are all of the greateſt importance.</p>
            <p>If only one ſort of men were able to underſtand them, as ſome would have it, we ſhould have had notice from Heaven, who thoſe ſhould be, and how qualified, and that in ſuch plain Characters, that it ſhould not be poſſible we ſhould miſtake; but there is no ſuch thing. And if any ſort of men claim this <hi>Arcanum</hi> above others, 'tis an affront to the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings of all the reſt and their Words ought not to be taken in their own Caſe. And indeed, 'tis a thing too great to be truſted with any one ſort of men: Some indeed will only have <hi>Learned Men</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of underſtanding them, but then if this ſhould be, what alamentable caſe the World would be in? Truth would then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>precarious</hi> thing, and we ſhould have no more of it than theſe <hi>Learned Men</hi> pleaſe, and if they ſhould be byaſſed, corrupted, or be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, what muſt the other three parts of the World do? Muſt they lie at their Mercy, and their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depend on their Honeſty? No, God forbid! And bleſſed be his Name, he has taken care men ſhall not lie liable to any ſuch Impoſtures. But if theſe men will needs be in the right above the reſt, and underſtand for them, let them do their duty for them too; for 'tis not reaſonable they ſhould be charged with a duty, that do not underſtand it. But having found their own failings herein, and that they are but men like others, during not to be ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as uſual, they betake themſelves to ſhifts; and to countenance their fallibility, ſupply the defects of honeſty, and ſalve their impoſition of their ſence; they ſet up a ſtrange ſort of Infallibility, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed would put an end to all the Diſputes and Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in Chiſtondom, were there any ſuch thing. But that which they have invented to put out the Flame, ſerves only to increaſe it; for where the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Infallibility is lodged, Heaven has given us no notice; which it would certainly have done, had there been any ſuch thing<hi>:</hi> And 'tis certain, that thoſe who pretend moſt to this Infallibility, have been moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of all.</p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> for the moſt part, have drove furiouſly, and forced all their People to do the ſame thing, and worſhip God the ſame way; but this cannot be called an Agreement, no more than Sheep are ſaid to agree, when they are drove up and Pounded all together by the Shepherd. And there is greater Agreement amongſt thoſe (though the fooliſh World think to the contrary) who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their Maker under the Adminiſtration of ſeveral Diſciplines, and Conduction of ſeveral Guides<hi>:</hi> For <hi>Force</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> may make a Congregation of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but no Unity of Minds. 'Tis only a Hearty Intention, Sincerity of Mind and Affections, Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleneſs and Identity of Addreſs to the ſame Object, which can be called Unity and Agreement, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe; for other things, though they may ſeem differences and diſagreements to men, yet really they are none at all; for the Circumſtances of Time and Place, Publick or Private, Day or Night, the ſeveral Inſtances of Reſpects, Methods and Way of Worſhip, are all one and the ſame thing to God Almighty; He only looks at the Unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Bond of Peace; Differences with men are not ſo with him, if they agree in ſincerity of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and integrity of Spirit; that's the Agreement he looks after.</p>
            <p>'Tis true again, That men underſtand the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures differently, and to different Senſes; but why this difference of Underſtanding ſhould be Objected as a Crime, I know not: For 'tis impoſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe, ſo long as there be ſuch great variety of Humane Underſtandings; and as long as they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not differently and amiſs on a <hi>bad end</hi> and <hi>deſign,</hi> they cannot poſſibly be <hi>Criminal;</hi> for no man is Obliged to underſtand better than he can. Then again, Many men may be totally Ignorant of many things in Scripture, and yet be very Innocent; and certainly if their Total Ignorance be no fault, their underſtanding differently thoſe things, which they might have been Innocently ignorant of, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make them guilty of a Crime; if it ſhould, it would highly advance Ignorance, and very much depreſs Underſtanding and Knowledge. But further, if they underſtand them differently (which I contend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for the moſt part they do) in order to promote a Virtue, encourage a Grace, or ſuppreſs a Vice, or any Immorality in themſelves, then this difference ought to be ſo far from being reputed a Crime, that it becomes Neceſſary, and ought to be Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged; and they that put a ſcandal on it, are very much to blame: And it muſt be allowed, that men may diſpute things in <hi>utramque partem,</hi> affirm and deny the ſame thing innocently enough, ſo the <hi>good intention</hi> be ſecured, and it be to edification, and make no infraction on Charity. But the things that become <hi>Criminal,</hi> are thoſe ſort of differences which every ſide and party of Chriſtians are but too guilty of, and which concerns them all to amend; and that is, Forcing an Interpretation on Scripture, contrary to the natural and genuine ſenſe thereof; and that with a deſign to countenance their own Intereſt or Party. And what the Papiſts Object, is but too
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41719:3"/>
true (though they have the leaſt reaſon to complain) that every one Interprets the Scripture to his Side and Party (and ſo do they to Theirs) and that the diviſions of Proteſtants have been principally occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by every on's having the uſe of the Scriptures; which admitting to be true, ſince theſe differences are unavoidable, and naturally Innocent in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and only <hi>accidentally</hi> evil, and much better at the worſt, than forced Agreements; one would think they ſhould have no further to Object: Since further, if the uſe of good things ſhould be denied and prohibited on the ſcore of their abuſe, and acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Inconveniencies, a juſt pretence might be brought in for all the Irregularities in the World.</p>
            <p>Now ſince the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> and <hi>Circumstantials</hi> in Religion are agreed on, ſince it has been made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear that every one may <hi>underſtand</hi> ſo much of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Scriptures, as is neceſſary for his Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſince 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> men ſhould not <hi>differ</hi> and <hi>diſagree,</hi> as alſo in moſt things not to be <hi>deceived,</hi> one would think theſe things ſhould make men mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and peaceable, and hinder the ill effect of any diſſention that might happen among them.</p>
            <p>But men are willing to admit and indulge one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a difference of Thought and Underſtanding in moſt of their Secular Concerns, but grow impatient, and are unwilling to admit any difference of Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the matters of Religion; and to their deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on this account, moſt of the Confuſions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of Chriſtendom owe their Original; and after the Unreaſonableneſs, Injuſtice and Folly of the thing has been made to appear to the World, one would think they ſhould ceaſe their mad and ineffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual proceedings.</p>
            <p>For it has been made to appear to the World, That <hi>Conſcience</hi> ought not to be <hi>conſtrained;</hi> that a <hi>Corporal</hi> Puniſhment ought not to be inflicted for a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Fault; that men ought not to <hi>Puniſh</hi> where they have no power to <hi>Command;</hi> that they cannot <hi>command</hi> the belief of a thing, unleſs they give a <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient</hi> Reaſon; and that, that can only be <hi>ſufficient,</hi> when the party is <hi>convinced;</hi> and that is not in their <hi>power</hi> to know, unleſs by the party acknowledged; that matters <hi>intellectual</hi> are not diſcerned by a <hi>Secular</hi> Power; that to puniſh men for differing in Opinion, is as unreaſonable as to puniſh them for having diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Faces; that no Humane Authority is either ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for cognizance or determination, or competent for infliction of puniſhment in ſuch matters; that the Terms of Schiſmatick and Heretick, are only Scare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crows, and ſignifie next to nothing; that no man is a Schiſmatick, but he that departs from a good Life, that fears not God, nor loves his Neighbour; and that no man is a Heretick, or ought to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as ſuch, but he that teaches ill Life, or takes up an ill Opinion contrary to Fundamentals, on a bad ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>viz.</hi> on the Score of Pride, Ambition, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, Malice, or any other Siniſter End, which will be very difficult to be known; that 'tis impoſſible for men not to differ, that 'tis not neceſſary they ſhould agres; that all Sorts and Parties of Chriſtians have been deceived; that amidſt ſo great difficulties, 'tis impoſſible they ſhould not be deceived; that Puniſhments ought to be proportioned to their Crimes; that <hi>Spiritual</hi> Faults ought only to have <hi>Spiritual</hi> Puniſhments; that a certain Puniſhment ought not to be inflicted for an uncertain Fault; that moſt Spiritual Faults are uncertain; that if a man was puniſhed or killed, he was certainly puniſhed or killed; but that it was not ſo certain he was in a Fault; that Concluſions ought not to be ſtronger than their Premiſes; that no man ought to be Judge in his own Caſe; that Reaſon, Diſcourſe and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the only Proper Methods and Inſtruments to Convince Men, and no other; that if others of an Heterogenial ſtamp were uſed, they might make Hypocrites, but no Proſelites, and that they were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver accompanied with ſucceſs; that the generality of men are diſpoſed to live quiet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; that Oppreſſion, Tyranny and Penal Laws, are occaſion of moſt of the Diſturbances in Chriſtendom; that fallible men ought not to call their Opinions Articles of Faith; that they ought not over-haſtily to intereſt their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker in their uncertain Cauſe; that God's Glory doth conſiſt with the Good of Men, and may be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without their Deſtruction. Further it hath been made evidently to appear againſt them, that ſay, <hi>We have a Law—</hi>That Law cannot make a Truth; that Truth is as old as the Eternal Veraci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and ſuffers no Degrees; for what was yeſterday, will be true to day, to morrow, and to the End of the World: And therefore to force People to be of their Religion, becauſe Eſtabliſhed by Law, is a great piece of Vanity and Nonſenſe: That neither Fathers, Councils, no Individual Man, or Company of Men, no Power or Force upon Earth are able to make a Truth, or an Article of Faith. No, all they are able to do, is by way of Promulgation, Declaration, or Explanation of Truth, but nothing by way of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; they may illuſtrate indeed, and make Truth appear to be ſo, but they cannot neither add or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh: What was Truth, and agreeable to God's Will, was ſo before, they undertook the Diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or before they came into the World, and will be ſo when they are extinct and gone out of it, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their endeavours for, or againſt it.</p>
            <p>Again, Nothing is more Certain than that Men are Men, and Uncertain; that they are, and have been proved fallible; That General Councils have erred and contradicted one another on Record; that Fathers have been miſtaken; that what has been, may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41719:3"/>
again; and therefore that all reſpectively may be uſed with reverence and reſpects as occaſion may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, as the beſt Humane Guides and Directors; but always with deference, and an eye to their Falli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility; that their Opinions ought not to be preſſed as Articles of Faith, nor their Determinations have the weight of Mathematical Demonſtrations. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks theſe Conſiderations ſhould make men look a little amicably on one another, and a little come to themſelves: But I find they do not, and may be the Scence is laid too far off; and therefore I will bring it nearer home, and let themſelves judge.</p>
            <p>A certain number of Pilgrims were going to the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> had equal deſires and affections for the Place, being all moved by the ſame Love and Good Intention; none indeed had been there already, and therefore they were the more to ſeek for their way; they were all very diligent to find out the true Road; and as they go along, they meet with ſeveral Ways and Paths; upon which the Company divided; ſome go one way, and ſome another, according as they thought it ſurer and more probable than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but ſome of the Company, of hotter Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution than the reſt, asked ſome of their Fellows, why they ſhould not go their way, ſince they were <hi>ſure</hi> they were in the right? To which they anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, They could not be <hi>ſure,</hi> becauſe they never were <hi>there;</hi> that they had the ſame Charts and Directions which they had, and had as honeſtly and ſincerely peruſed them; induced by the ſame, if not greater Love and Affection to the Place; and that they did not think that way to be right, but that the Path they were going in, was the ſurer and more probable way, and hoped that it would bring them to the Place as ſoon, if not ſooner than theirs would, and therefore deſired to be excuſed; adding, That if they ſhould go with them, they ſhould go againſt their Thoughts and Conſciences, which would be a trouble to them all along the Road, but eſpecially at laſt, if they ſhould be miſtaken. This anſwer, though modeſt and very reaſonable, yet was not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory; for the other preſſed them hard, loving Company very well, and ſaid, That ſince they were all going to the ſame place, 'twas fit they ſhould all go together in the ſame Road; and if they would not, they would take away their Proviſions and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and force them: And their Paſſions and Zeal was ſo hot, that they did ſo, and worſe; for ſome they beat, and others they killed; and for the Reſt, at the next Town they prevailed ſo with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and miſrepreſented them ſo ill, that they got them put in durance.</p>
            <p>Now who can but pity the hard fate of theſe poor Pilgrims? Or forbear to Cenſure and give his Verdict againſt the hot fiery Zeal of the other? But let them ſpeak as dare: Whoever pities them, I ſhall ſay to them as <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>David, You are the Men;</hi> All ſides have been too but Guilty, and have plaid the ſame Pranks when in Power.</p>
            <p>One would wonder how Chriſtian men ſhould have ſuch Hatred and Animoſities one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and run Counter to all the Principles of their Religion, and Laws of their Great Maſter; <hi>Whoſe Leſſons,</hi> as one ſaid, <hi>were ſofter than Nard, or the Juice of the Candian Olive;</hi> teaching all imaginable Compliance, mutual Forbearance and Charity; and one of his laſt Commands to them was, <hi>To love one another;</hi> but they have not minded the Commands of their Good Lord, or obſerved the advice of their Compaſſionate <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but have fallen out by the Way, diſhonoured their Profeſſion, and ruined them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>But a man ſhall quickly be raiſed from his wonder, when he conſiders the miſtakes under which they lie.</p>
            <p>They greatly miſtake in calling their Reſpective <hi>Opinions,</hi> Several <hi>Religions:</hi> I affirm there is but ONE God, and ONE Religion; and that they may as well call the ſeveral Counties in <hi>England,</hi> ſeveral Nations, as to give ſeveral Opinions, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination of ſeveral diſtinct Religions. We ask a man what Countryman he is? If he tells us <hi>Darby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, Stafford-ſhire,</hi> all is well, there is no hurt done; but if we ask him what Religion he is off, and it prove to be differing from ours; preſently an Animoſitie ariſes, and we look on him with ſtrange thoughts, and reckon him almoſt ſomething elſe than a <hi>Man,</hi> and rather a <hi>Heathen</hi> than a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and when we have made him ſuch a <hi>Heathen,</hi> then we think, like the <hi>Iſraelites, That 'tis Lawful to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy ſuch a</hi> Canaanite <hi>from among us;</hi> never conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering all this while the mans Conſtitution, Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Prejudice, the Books he may have Read, the Company he may have kept, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which may make him have different thoughts and apprehenſions of things from ours, and that his Honeſty and good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention may make his Sentimens (though differing from ours) yet altogether as Innocent.</p>
            <p>Again, 'Tis a ſtrange vanity that men have, in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing themſelves ſo extreamly for being of this or that perſwaſion or party of men, and brings a great deal of trouble to the World. One ſaith he is a Catholick and no Heretick; the Proteſtant-Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks ſay, they are good Proteſtants and no Papiſts; and the Church-of-England-man ſaith, he is of a Religion eſtabliſhed by Law, and no Diſſenter; as if Law could make a Truth; and ſo they go on, upbraiding one another, ſuppoſing every Diviſion of Chriſtians that has a diſtinct Name, is a diſtinct Religion. Now if we ſhould be ſo fooliſh in other concerns, what would the World think of us? If the <hi>Yorkſhire-men</hi> ſhould ſay the <hi>Kentiſh-men</hi> are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41719:4"/>
no <hi>Engliſh</hi> men; or the <hi>Merchant-Taylors</hi> tell the <hi>Mercers</hi> they are no Citizens, would not the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters be expoſed to deriſion? Further, if a man calls not himſelf by ſome name or other, as Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. Church-of-England-man, Presbyterian, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he is look'd upon as a piece of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced or Antiquated Coin that will not paſs: If he ſay he is a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that will not ſatisfie; he runs ſome hazard in calling himſelf by that Name; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or none in not departing from Iniquity: if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ls himſelf <hi>Lutheran, Calvinist, Zuinglian, &amp;c.</hi> all will be well, he is ſorted, and hath Fellows, ſhall be reſpected and eſteemed; but if be will eſpouſe none of their Factions, nor intereſt himſelf in their ſimple Quarrels, he is branded with the odious Name of Atheiſt, or to be of no Religion at all. And ſuch a high pitch of Extravagancy is the World come to, that a <hi>Jew</hi> in a Chriſtian Nation ſhall have more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect than a Chriſtian; and that for no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but becauſe he calls himſelf ſo. Should a man be ſo hardy as to leave <hi>Paul, Apollos</hi> and <hi>Cephas,</hi> and call himſelf by that Venerable Name, which requires ſome courage; 'tis odds but he may be called to an account for raiſing a New Religion; his imitation of his Holy Life would not ſatisfie the mad World; if he cannot pronounce <hi>Shiboleth</hi> plainly, and herd himſelf with a Party, there's none will take him into their Folds, but out he ſhall lie in the Fields, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the mercy of the Elements. But all this might be cured in a great meaſure, if the State would put a Fine on thoſe that call themſelves by any other Name, than that of Chriſtian. For 'tis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible to think what miſchiefs go along with theſe New Names; O, he is a Papiſt, ſays one; he's a Fana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick, ſays another; they are Words of reproach, and their meaning is, he is an ill man; for ſo every Side and Party accepts them one againſt another: And ſome, when they would go a ſhorter way to work, call but their Adverſary by the name of his Sect, that ſerves for Evidence, Conviction and Condemnation; and then ſecure him Goaler. But it will be asked, and ought to be enquired into, How they came by ſuch falſe Notions of things? Then I ſay,</p>
            <p>That Cuſtom, Chance, Prejudice and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, give moſt men their way of Religion, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates their Conſciences too; they think this or that to be ſinful, not which is really and naturally ſo, but what they ſee ſome men abhor and deteſt, and what they have been taught is ſo; and Youth generally take their Parents word, and ſwallow all infinitely and implicitly; and if one be miſtaken, 'tis hardly poſſible but that the other will be miſtaken too. And 'tis certain, that the undutifulneſs of diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parents injunctions, and the reproach and ſhame of being ſingular, and doing things contrary to their Country Cuſtoms and Uſages, are great Obſtacles to Truth and Peace. Some of the <hi>Indians</hi> did eat their dead Friends and Relations, and thought it a great piece of Piety, and the moſt honourable way of Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but the <hi>Greeks</hi> they burned them all: <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> asked each of them, what he ſhould give them to exchange their Method? They both anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the greateſt abhorrence imaginable, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed againſt each others Uſages, as the moſt barbarous and undecent way in the World.</p>
            <p>Cuſtom makes good things to ſeem evil, and evil things to ſeem good. And I have read of a Shepherd on the Mountains of <hi>Naples,</hi> who in the holy time of <hi>Lent,</hi> came with Tears in his Eyes to his Confeſſor, and earneſtly deſired Abſolution, in that he had ſwallowed by chance a little Whey, which leaped into his Mouth from the Cheeſe-Preſs: The Father asked him, <hi>Whether he knew himſelf guilty of no other Sins?</hi> He anſwered, <hi>Not any as he knew of.</hi> He again asked him, <hi>Whether he was not acceſſary to any of the Robberies and Murders committed on their Mountains? Yes indeed,</hi> Quoth he, <hi>that I am; but this we never esteem a Crime; 'tis a thing daily practiſed by all of us, and there needs no confeſſion for ſuch things.</hi> By this may be ſeen what Cuſtom can do. But Education, Prejudice and Cuſtom, have ſtill further ſtrange Operations. For,</p>
            <p>They ſtrangely diſpoſe men to be reſolute and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious of their firſt-taught-Principles, and make them Deaf to the moſt Weighty, Sober and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing Reaſons; and when a man is linked to a Party, there is no unchaining of him; he delights in his Slavery and Chains, and reckons him an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that would free him: He will be of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he was bred to, whether <hi>Turk, Jew,</hi> or <hi>Pagan;</hi> and thinks that always the beſt: Come to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him, and he looks on you as an Impoſtor, and all the Arguments you ſhall bring, ſignifie no more than Arrows againſt a Wall of Braſs; he is reſolved, ſay what you will, you ſhall not move him; he will not conſider any thing that is alledged againſt him; will laugh at your Reaſons, ſhift them off, and do any thing rather than be <hi>Convinced;</hi> nay he comes with a Reſolution to a Diſcourſe, <hi>not to be overcome;</hi> and to ſay ſomething for his <hi>Side,</hi> rather than the <hi>Truth;</hi> and what is worſt of all, 'tis impoſſible ſome ſhould be prevailed upon, who eſteem all Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be <hi>Temptations,</hi> and therefore look upon themſelves obliged by all means to ſhun them.</p>
            <p>So that this ſort of Obſtinacy and Perverſneſs, this Partiality, this reſpect to Perſons and Sides, and want of Sincerity, and Indifferency to Truth, keeps a foot our Differences, obſtructs mutual Complian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Toleration; every one calling his <hi>Fancy</hi> his Faith, his <hi>Opinion</hi> his Religion, and entitles <hi>God</hi> to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41719:4"/>
all; and when <hi>God</hi> is concerned, then they think their Zeal cannot be <hi>too much;</hi> and out of an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to Lukewarmneſs, endeavour to make it as <hi>Hot as</hi> they can; <hi>ſo Hot,</hi> that it deſtroys <hi>Charity,</hi> and Burns and Preys upon their innocent Neighbours.</p>
            <p>But a further Acceſſary (and Aggravation too) of Chriſtian Differences, is the Method and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of their Government. For Firſt, They ſuppoſe God Almighty has appointed a particular Diſcipline and Regiment for his Church, and then fall out about it; every one maintaining that their own particular Scheme is the ſame: Then again, they ſuppoſe that <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Regiment</hi> is abſolutely neceſſary; both which are falſe: I or God neither hath appointed any <hi>particular Way,</hi> neither is any <hi>neceſſary,</hi> any further than for the neceſſary Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating ſuch Aſſemblies as ſhall meet together to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip their God; or to <hi>Excommunicate</hi> a man out of ſuch their Aſſemblies for his evil Life; which are things very eaſie to be done, and need no great Wit or Learning to perform: And any man may be <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, Juſt, True, Sincere, Charitable, Humble,</hi> and Exerciſe any Chriſtian Graces or Vertues, without the help of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Policy;</hi> he may Pray to, or Praiſe his God in Spirit and Truth, (which is all the Way that ever Chriſt appointed) without the help of Church-Policy. Chriſt's Kingdom is of another World, and requires none of the Policy of this to manage it; it ought to be kept pure and unmix'd, being clear of another Nature: We ſee Oyl in a Veſſel of Water will not mix, but keep its Body in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire to it ſelf, no more ought Spirituals to be mix'd with Temporals. But theſe Spiritual Politicians have mix'd Heaven and Earth together, confounded the World with their Policy, and ſo jumbled things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, that Chriſtianity is almoſt loſt in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> ſo that men know not where to find it. I ſhould think that the ill ſucceſs and bad effects ſuch <hi>Policy</hi> hath hitherto had in the World, ſhould make them aſhamed, and endeavour by all means to leave ſuch methods, which did always rather <hi>Diſturb,</hi> than any way <hi>Beautifie</hi> the Church of God. And let them further give me leave to tell them, That if all the Hedges and Encloſures in <hi>England</hi> were pulled down and levelled, that it would be <hi>England-ſtill:</hi> 'Tis True, Property might ſuffer by ſuch a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication; but to Heaven and Religion, every one has an equal Title and Property.</p>
            <p>And if God Almighty had deſign'd a <hi>particular Way</hi> or Method of Worſhip, he would have taken care that none ſhould miſs it, and prevented <hi>all Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences</hi> about it. But he has appointed <hi>none</hi> at all, as I know of, but that of <hi>in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> And had any particular Way been abſolutely neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, our Saviour would have told the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> when ſhe did as good as ask him the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>How, or where they ſhould worſhip God? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>or</hi> Samaria? (For there was a great conteſt about it amongſt the Inhabitants of each) But he told her, <hi>That the time was come, that they ſhould neither Worſhip him at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>nor</hi> Samaria; that is, not at either of thoſe places in particular, excluſive of others, <hi>but in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> As if he had ſaid, The <hi>Times</hi> of limitation of God's Worſhip is now over: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> indeed was the place appointed, and particular Rites and Ceremonies were enjoyned and made obligatory; but now thoſe times are paſt, all Rites, Types and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies are aboliſhed, and other <hi>Times</hi> are come, that God muſt be Worſhipped after another manner. I obſerve you mind Times and Places, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Methods <hi>too much;</hi> and have fooliſh and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Contentions for the ſame, and mind Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity <hi>too little;</hi> therefore I aſſign and appoint you no particular Place, Method, or Time: But be ſure when ever you Worſhip God, let it be ſincerely and heartily, let it be <hi>in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> and you ſhall then be accepted.</p>
            <p>Now men have ſtrange Contentions about the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Way</hi> of God's Worſhip, but do but grope in the dark, ſince no way is appointed: I do not ſay they do amiſs, if they mean well; but the <hi>Truth</hi> of the <hi>Action</hi> I reckon is the principal thing, by how much more eaſie it is to be performed, and more earneſtly of God required; for he ſaith, <hi>Son give me thy Heart.</hi> And 'tis an eaſie thing for any man to know whether he is in Earneſt, whether he is Sincere, Hearty and Real, in what he doth; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he Loves, or Fears, or truly Worſhips God or no; whether the Affections of the Soul accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany his Actions, and that he is no Hypocrite: This, I ſay, is eaſie for any man of the <hi>meaneſt Capacity</hi> to tell: But then whether the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of our Worſhip be in a <hi>true Way,</hi> is not ſo ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily found out, for the Reaſons aforementioned, and the great <hi>Difficulties</hi> therein. And if after Diligence uſed, (ſince no particular way is appointed) we miſtake in chooſing inſtances of Reſpect to our Maker; our miſtakes are <hi>Invincible,</hi> and we ſhall never be anſwerable for them: But if we be, 'tis only to him <hi>Our Lord,</hi> and not to <hi>One Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> And therefore 'tis the moſt unreaſonable thing imaginable, for men to judge one another in theſe points, much more to impoſe their reſpective Fancies and Models, with inſufferable Penalties, one upon another, when they can have ſo <hi>little Aſſurance</hi> they are in the Right.</p>
            <p>But while I am endeavouring to Cool and Qualifie the Mad World by Reaſons and Arguments, dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting theiir Miſtakes, and expoſing to View the Unneceſſary Occaſions of their Differences, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41719:5"/>
Unreaſonableneſs of their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive Contentions, I am pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Wakes</hi> Text at St. <hi>Laurence</hi> and <hi>Mercers</hi> Chappel.</note> Interrupted with a Text of Scripture lakely Preached in the City; and that is, <hi>Contend earneſtly for the Faith once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Saints.</hi> What, ſays ſome, would you not have us <hi>contend</hi> for the Faith? Would you not have us <hi>earneſt</hi> for our Religion, and for the Truth? I reply, Yes by any means: And this Text doth encourage you to <hi>contend</hi> not only for the <hi>True Faith</hi> and <hi>True Religion,</hi> but alſo for <hi>That</hi> Faith, and <hi>That</hi> Religion which you believe to be ſo; for that is the <hi>ſame</hi> to <hi>you</hi> as the True, and no difference can, or ought to be made: And then this Text, if not duly tempered and moderated, is ſufficient to ſet all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom together by the Ears; for every Party and Sect think their <hi>own way</hi> of Religion and Faith to be Primitive, Apoſtolical and True; and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, have a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from this Text to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend earneſtly</hi> for it: And ſome have acted ſo <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly,</hi> and depend ſo much on the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of their <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>trueneſs</hi> of their <hi>Faith,</hi> that they have Plundered, Impriſoned, nay Killed and Murdered their fellow Chriſtians; to teſtifie to the World their <hi>Earneſtneſs,</hi> and that they were in <hi>Earneſt;</hi> but in my Opinion, they had much better been in <hi>Jeſt,</hi> than ſo Extravagantly <hi>Earneſt.</hi> Therefore this <hi>Earneſtneſs</hi> muſt be limited, ſo that it be not Prejudicial to our ſelves, or Deſtructive to others: It ought to be managed with the greateſt Cautiouſneſs, Prudence and Diſcretion; and by no other Inſtruments, but thoſe of Perſwaſion and Ratiocination.</p>
            <p>Now leſt People ſhould be ſo much in earneſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as formerly, the Wiſe, Judicious and Loving Father of our Countrey, would put Bounds to ſuch deſtructive <hi>Earneſtneſs,</hi> which hath made ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſtations among his People; he would take their Weapons out of their Hands, with which they have done ſo much Miſchief: But they like fooliſh Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, are Peeviſh and Froward, exert their Paſſions; grow Angry, are Sullen and Diſcontented, run and make their Moan to their Mother; whoſe too In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgent Nature and Tender Heart, is but too much Grieved to ſee her Children out of Humour; and is almoſt ready to Sacrifice their future Happineſs and Proſperity, to their preſent Quiet and Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But what ſhould be done in this Caſe, is an Impertinent Queſtion: For the Diſcretion and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Father, ought to prevail againſt the Over-fondneſs of the Indulgent Mother, and the Peeviſhneſs of the Humourſome Children; if they cry for Knives to cut them, Candles to burn them, or Food that is unwholeſome for them; they muſt be ſilenced, and no notice taken of their Childiſh Demands. So that after what has been ſaid and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Methinks 'tis the moſt Unreaſonable, Undutiful and Shameful Oppoſition imaginable, which ſome go about to make againſt his Majeſty; that when he endeavours to make an <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> of a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and offers to put it out of the Power of any one Party to <hi>Hurt</hi> or <hi>Diſturb</hi> another, and that by as good <hi>Humane Security</hi> as poſſibly can be contriv'd, they ſhould ſo Obſtinately and Childiſhly reject it. That when it has been made ſo plainly appear, that <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests</hi> have been the Ruine, and do Ruine the Nation; and will Ruine any Nation, that maintain them: That they are moſt Unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, Unjuſt and Uncharitable, and yet Maintained and Continued; Good God, that men ſhould be ſo Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid! What can this Argue, but that Heaven has no kindneſs for ſuch men: But ſeeing their Obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Perverſeneſs, gives them over to Court their own Ruine and Deſtruction; and, ſay I, <hi>May the Rods be continued on ſuch Fools Backs, ſince they are ſo fond of them.</hi> For my part, I think to be clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped up in a Goal, to be Fined, Plundred, Wounded or Killed, on the Score of meer Religion, and for having different Thoughts and Apprehenſions from other men; is a Reproach to the Chriſtian World, and the moſt Brutiſh, Irrational and Shamefulleſt thing imaginable; and I think it every mans Duty to endeavour to Extirpate ſuch a Wicked Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>For me to be puniſhed for being a <hi>Man,</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieing when there is <hi>Reaſon</hi> given, or an <hi>Argument</hi> which <hi>ſeems to me</hi> to be Reaſon (which is the ſame thing) is a thing I can ſcarce think of with Patience. I know, to Countenance ſuch Unjuſtifiable Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, there is a Black Charge advanced; and that is Heretick, Schiſmatick, Turbulency of Spirit, Unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Enemies to Government, Plotters, Seditious, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, Ungrateful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe are the common Topicks of Scandal which one Party charges the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with, when they have got them under, or have abuſed them: They think to charge others with Faults, is to make themſelves <hi>Innocent;</hi> and the World would cry out on them, ſhould they not have ſome ugly thing to lay to their Charge, after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo unhandſomly treated them. But theſe Aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions have been wiped off over and over; and it has been ſaid, <hi>If it be enough to Accuſe, who ſhall be Innocent?</hi> The Charge alſo has been returned on the Accuſers Heads, to whom indeed it belongs: For Tyrants and Oppreſſors blow the Coals, and then make Wonders at, and accuſe the Flame: They won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der men will not be Quiet, and accuſe them of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, when <hi>They</hi> are their only Diſturbers, and occaſion of all the Commotion, by Oppreſſing them, and Puniſhing them without a Cauſe. <hi>They</hi> make multitudes of <hi>Penai Laws,</hi> and by Conſequence <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Delinguents.</hi> The fewer the <hi>Penal Laws</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41719:5"/>
are, the more Quietneſs and Peace always there is in the World; and thoſe were happy Ages, when<hi>—Verba minantia fixo are, legebantur—</hi>Every man might go but to the Market Croſs, and read pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently his Duty, what he was to do, and what to avoid. The plain Truth is, the multitudes of <hi>Penal Laws</hi> do but muſter up, and ſhow the World how ſtrong they are in Delinquents; and when they ſee their Numbers, they take Courage, and preſently Conſpire (animated by their being equally Obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) to throw off their Yoke and Government, that hath made them all <hi>ſuch Criminals,</hi> and Subjected them to Puniſhment, for things in their own nature Innocent; and ſuch Laws proves generally fatal to the Makers.</p>
            <p>Further it hath been made to appear, that 'tis a moſt Unreaſonable and Unjuſt Thing, that a King ſhould come to a Crown, and not to have the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and Service of all his Subjects indifferently: That thoſe Laws which qualifie one ſort of men only for his Service, are too Partial and Unjuſt; and put it into the Power of thoſe men to do with him what they pleaſe; That 'tis not fit nor ſafe for a Prince to have but one Staff to lean on, or one Weapon to defend himſelf; That 'tis Unreaſonable and Unjuſt that any one ſort of men, under what Denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever, ſhould engroſs all Honours and Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to themſelves; and have all the Favour of the Prince, and only ſit in the <hi>Sunſhine,</hi> and all the reſt in the <hi>Shade;</hi> whoſe Fidelity and Integrity to their Prince, their Sufficiency and Ability in Buſineſs; their Peaceable Temper, and equal, if not more proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Arguments for the truth of their Religion; ſet them on equal ground, and give them as large and juſt a Claim thereto as others: That ſuch Diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating and Partial Laws, do naturally tend to put the Kingdom in Confuſion; and as long as one Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (as they call it) receives an Eſtabliſhment, and another doth not, that has equal Pretentions to it, <hi>there will never be Peace and Quiet in</hi> England.</p>
            <p>Again, It has been proved, that Laws are Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally Null and Void, and grow into Deſuetude, and need no formality of a Repeal; after the Reaſons for which they were Enacted, are taken away; or when they bring ſo many Inconveniences, which out-bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance their Advantages. A Law, for good Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is made, That for the ſpace of Ten Years, none ſhall preſume to Kill or Deſtroy ſuch a ſort of Wild Beaſts; but in the ſpace of Five Years they grow ſo numerous and unruly, that they come into the Neighbouring Towns, and make great Havock, and deſtroy the Inhabitants: Will any man deny the men of the place the priviledge of killing them, and charge them with a Breach of the Law? No ſure I Such Laws loſe their Obligation, and ought to loſe their Denominations too; and to be called ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſt than Laws, rather than <hi>Grievances,</hi> or <hi>Nutſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> which they really are, and ought to do no Miſchief under the ſpecious Title of Laws. His Majeſty is charged with breach of Laws, for taking ſuch <hi>Nuiſances</hi> away; methinks they ſhould rather thank him for ſuch Low <hi>Condeſcention,</hi> it being the <hi>Scavengers</hi> Office. If unruly Fire break out in our Buildings, a Door is admitted to be broken open, or a neighbouring Houſe to be blown up, and no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice charged. 'Tis His Majeſty's Caſe; He pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not to put the Fires out of men's Chimneys, or to Cancel any wholſome or neceſſary Laws, but to put a ſtop to the Outrage and Violence of thoſe Fiery, Cruel and Sanguinary Laws, that have made ſuch Havock amongſt his People; and if ſo much Power muſt not be allowed him, he has not Power enough to <hi>Defend Himſelf,</hi> or His <hi>People.</hi> But this Oppoſition being made by Intereſted and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Men, is leſs to be taken notice of: And I queſtion not, but will be over-ruled by Him, who is not <hi>Partial</hi> as they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e; but conſults the Good of the whole, and will not let any one ſort of men have Power to Oppreſs the reſt. But then again, as to our Differences:</p>
            <p>I am utterly againſt reconciling of them by ſuch Methods, which ſome men take; and am indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent whether they be reconciled or no; ſo they may be made <hi>Harmleſs</hi> and <hi>Eaſie</hi> to the Publick: And I do proteſt, I cannot ſee ſo much <hi>Iniquity</hi> in them, as ſome would perſwade; and hardly know how to call them <hi>Differences,</hi> but obſerve more their <hi>Agreement</hi> than their <hi>Difference.</hi> For all do mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually <hi>agree</hi> to Worſhip the ſame Eternal Ever-Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, and believe in his Ever-Bleſſed Son Jeſus Chriſt. The <hi>Differences</hi> I moſt obſerve, are <hi>Men's Differences,</hi> and mutual Animoſities about <hi>Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences.</hi> And I affirm, the <hi>firſt Differences</hi> in the various modes of Worſhip, are moſtly <hi>Innocent;</hi> but the <hi>ſecond Differences</hi> are Criminal; that is, men's differing one with another, and inflicting Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments one upon another about them; and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Bonds of Charity; hating and denying Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion one to another, on the ſcore of any way of Worſhip, <hi>differing</hi> from theirs, though altogether as Innocent.</p>
            <p>And what I have ſaid before, is not with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to make all Men to be of one and the ſame Mind to have the ſame Thoughts and Apprehenſions of things; to agree and perform the ſame things, after the ſame Manner and Method, as ſome Men are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-fond of, and lay out all their endeavours (but to no purpoſe) to bring to paſs; for this is neither <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible</hi> nor <hi>neceſſary;</hi> and therefore do rather incourage honeſt and <hi>ſincere Differences,</hi> than ſuch forced and <hi>Hypocritical Agreements:</hi> For what ſignifies a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation and Preſence of Bodies, when there is a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41719:6"/>
diſſent and abſence of Minds? 'Tis the Unity of Minds makes the Agreement; and though Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Univerſality may ſeem fine and plauſible things to men, yet they cannot be pleaſing in the ſight of God, if accompanied with Error or Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, which are generally the Concomitants of <hi>pack'd Agreements:</hi> But we know that he is well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with our ſincerity and good intentions; and will rather Pity than Puniſh, our unwilling and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate miſtakes, in our various and differing Methods and Inſtances of Reſpect unto him. But my deſign is from the <hi>Impoſſibility</hi> of men's Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, about the things they contend, from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency</hi> of their firſt Differences, from the Folly and Vanity of their Contention; all aiming at, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning the ſame things, <hi>viz. The Salvation of their own Souls, and the Glory of God;</hi> to perſwade men to calm, quiet and ſoften their Minds, and to convince them of the Unreaſonableneſs of their Mutual Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities and Impoſitions, and to diſpoſe them to Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Compliances and Charity: Alſo I would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenance, as much as poſſible, the fooliſh and vain Attemps of thoſe Men, who with all the Art and Induſtry imaginable, do endeavour to make the World all of <hi>One Mind;</hi> &amp; are impatient of any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction and D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſent. 'Tis ſtrange that the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of ſo many Ages ſhould not School them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a better Underſtanding; let them quote the Age wherein they all agreed: Has there not been Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt Father, Council againſt Council, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of Changes and Innovations? And have we not tranſmitted to us a Black Liſt of Hereſies and Schiſms, (as men call them?) And 'tis poſſible they may quote an Univerſal Force and Tyranny, but never an Univerſal Agreement. But why ſhould I go on? Theſe are things paſt Contradiction, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what hopes is there now to make Men all of <hi>One Mind,</hi> more than formerly? Have we not <hi>Their</hi> Difficulties, and our <hi>Own</hi> too, to contend with? And to ſay true, we have nothing handed down cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and not ſubject to diſpute, but the Good Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weadore, and his only begotten Son, in whom we believe. Theſe things indeed are Univerſally Credited amongſt us, and not diſputed by any. But all other things do, and may challenge a Diſpute, ſince they have paſſed through ſo many differing Hands, and ſerved ſo many different Intereſts and Parties. Indeed ſome Records I reckon more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick than others, I mean thoſe that teach and inſtruct us in the ways of Peace and Holy-Living; but in general, all lie more or leſs liable to exception. For they have been managed by men of various and differing Underſtandings, Paſſions, Humours, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions and Intereſts. And have we not the ſame ſort of men? And is not the World governed by the ſame Methods and Politicks as formerly? We ſee every party quote Scripture, and Fathers and Councils one againſt another. But to what purpoſe? For none of them at this time of the day, after the Revolution of ſo many years, are competent or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to decide our Differences: Every Age brings up Men of Prudence and Diſcretion enough to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern themſelves; and what the Fathers did is not to be drawn down for a Preſident for theſe Time: They lived in Ages wherein their Civil Cuſtoms were different from ours; and their Civil Cuſtoms may as well be impoſed on us, as their Eccleſiaſtical; their Civil Cuſtoms did influence their Eccleſiaſtical, and ſo doth ours; and that increaſes the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: Beſides, they were but <hi>Men,</hi> and ſo are <hi>We:</hi> They were <hi>Good Men</hi> indeed, and lived Holy Lives, and were Ornaments to their reſpective Generations; and as ſuch we ought to reſpect them. But there is too much reverence paid to Antiquity by ſome; and they are apt to draw very weak Concluſions; and ſay, <hi>Such a Father ſaid ſuch a thing; Ergo,</hi> 'tis true; and think this way of Arguing is Good and Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick; never conſidering the Truth and Reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Thing, ſo much as the Authority of the Man. But further, paſſing over the Iniquity of the Times, and the Corruptions which they may have undergone; and ſuppoſing them to be all truly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to us, yet they will ſignifie very little at beſt, ſince every Diſputer and Party is to manage them: They will ſpeak any thing we would have them to ſpeak; and are Weapons in the Hands of every one that pleaſes to take them: And nothing is more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon than to hear all Sides and Parties ſay, <hi>They have Reaſon, Scriptures, Fathers and Councils on their Side;</hi> but this ſignifies nothing at all, becauſe they muſt not be Judges in their own Caſe. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they ſignifie, as to particular men for inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and direction in Holy Living; and give Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Councel and Advice, and miniſter to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Piety, but will decide few of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, ſince Parties muſt manage them. 'Tis certain that Law, Scripture, Argument and Reaſon, ſignifies little amongſt Diſputers; each Party cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that <hi>Law,</hi> which doth ſerve their <hi>Turns;</hi> that <hi>Scripture,</hi> which doth ſeem to countenance their <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion;</hi> and that <hi>Reaſon</hi> and good <hi>Argument,</hi> which favours and tends to promote their <hi>Deſign;</hi> and not what <hi>really</hi> are ſo: And this miſery will ſtill be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the World, as long as we have ſeveral Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts to manage; ſeveral Parties, and ſo few (if any) indifferent, and impartial Judges amongſt us; and all things will ſuffer Aggravation or Extenuation, be great or little, good or bad; according as they quadrate with mens Opinions, Prejudices or Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts. But ſuppoſing men to be Impartial, Diligent and Honeſt, yet 'tis impoſſible they ſhould not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in their Sentiments, ſince their Underſtandings
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41719:6"/>
are ſo various: And ſome underſtand more, ſome leſs than is meant; ſome Figuratively, ſome Literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſome Relatively, others Collectively, Diſtributive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Privitively, Poſitively, Affirmatively, Negatively, and a hundred other ways, to the <hi>wearying</hi> and <hi>wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out</hi> of all the Adverbs; Witneſs all thoſe nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and large Comments and Explications on Law and Goſpel, both by Ancient and Modern Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, moſt differing one from the other, though on the ſame Texts; according to the Capacities, differing Acquirements, Educations, Prejudices, or Prior No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Managers, all which add to the Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Mens Agreement. Then again, Affection being founded in Likeneſs; the various Authors find Abetters, according as they find Readers of the ſame Humour and Conſtitutions: One loves ſuch a Book, and ſuch a Man; and ſaith, What he writes is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Truth and Right; and why? Not that it really is ſo; but becauſe he writes ſomething ſuitable to his Genius and Complexion: The Sanguine loves the Chearful and Encouraging; the Melancholy, the moſt Doleful and Tragical Expoſition; and moſt call that which <hi>pleaſes them,</hi> the <hi>Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further, Let them tell me what good they have done, by ſuch their Endeavours of Uniting Men, as they call it? Have they no raiſed more Devils than they can lay? Has not one Book begot another, and one Diſpute another? And ſo <hi>like</hi> is <hi>Truth</hi> to <hi>Falſhood,</hi> and <hi>one thing</hi> to <hi>another;</hi> and there be ſo many Plauſibilities and Probabilities, the Wiſeſt and moſt Conſidering Man may be deceived; and ſo by Conſequence this Humour of Diſputing propagated to the end of the World; which inſtead of Curing and Healing Differences, doth but enlarge the Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and increaſe them, by <hi>raiſing</hi> Mens Paſſions, and <hi>deſtroying</hi> Charity. As to <hi>publick</hi> Diſputes, 'twas hardly ever known but they that had moſt Power, and the largeſt Intereſt, always went away with the Victory. And as for <hi>private,</hi> I ſcarce ever knew two Perſons engaged in a Diſpute, but that both came off <hi>worſe,</hi> though both got the <hi>better:</hi> The <hi>love</hi> of Victory on one hand, and the <hi>ſhame</hi> of being overcome on the other; their Paſſion and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet Zeal, their Weakneſs or Intereſt, hath made them ſo obſtinate and reſolute, and put them on ſuch Shifts and Artifices, that have made them come off worſe Men, I am ſure <hi>worſe Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then it muſt be allowed me, that 'tis impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible the World ſhould agree, or be all of <hi>one Mind</hi> in matters of Religion, and no means found <hi>competent</hi> to make them ſo; to what end then do Men Diſpute? Do they think to Unite the Poles, or reconcile Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions? Indeed their Endeavours may be pitied, becauſe they mean well; but not at all to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended. But to ſpeak Truth, they have ſeen the impoſſibility of their Attempt long ago, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore laid their Heads together for an Expedient to ſalve all. Hence came the concern of <hi>Infallibility a poor ſhift</hi> indeed, which hath made all things worſe than they were before; and has been ſo often baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled, and is ſuch a ridiculous thing, ſo much againſt the Experience of all Mankind, that Laughing at it is the beſt way of Arguing. And to my Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the more Certain and Infallible Truth, of the <hi>Impoſſibility of Agreement,</hi> is a much better <hi>Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> to charm the mad World into an Agreement, than that of Infallibility: For when after ſo much Experience, and ſo many Attempts made, Men find the <hi>impoſſibility</hi> of Agreement; methinks they ſhould at laſt agree; that is, they ſhould yield them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Vanquiſhed; ſee their Faults and Vanity of Contention, be induced to be at Peace one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; ceaſe their mutual Violence and Severity, and Amicably turn all into mutual Love, Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Charity. And when the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> boaſt of their <hi>Agreement</hi> and <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and object it to the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that they cannot agree; I would have them tell them again, that 'tis <hi>impoſſible</hi> to agree, nor is it <hi>neceſſary;</hi> and that it is no Crime to <hi>diſagree</hi> in their Senſe. Alſo that their <hi>Agreement,</hi> however they may boaſt, is no <hi>Agreement;</hi> that the <hi>Fagots</hi> may as well be ſaid to <hi>agree,</hi> when they are bound up together, or <hi>Sheep</hi> when drove up together and pounded in their Folds; and that it is rather a Combination, or any thing in the World, more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per than an Agreement.</p>
            <p>And let me ask the World the Queſtion, Where the Harm would be, if Men Worſhip their Maker in their <hi>own</hi> way; and have various and different Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Things; if all their reſpective Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Sentiments be ſecured from having <hi>ill Effects</hi> on the Publick, and from diſturbing one another? What is that to me, if a Man think a Tree to be a Man, or a Man to be a Beaſt; if a Man ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thought and apprehended, be ſecured from being baited or worried? We are all to anſwer to one common Lord and Maſter; <hi>He</hi> is to be our Judge, if we have ſerved him not right: Indeed, I look on it as my Duty to inform my Neighbour, and inſtruct him, if he be out of the way, if I think <hi>my way</hi> the better, and more pleaſing to my Maker. But then, ſince <hi>I</hi> may be miſtaken, and out of the way, and <hi>he</hi> in the right way, my method with him ought to be no other than Reaſon and Diſcourſe; and that in the moſt moderate and diſcreet way I can. For if I ſhould do otherwiſe, I may bring a <hi>greater</hi> Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience on him, than <hi>that</hi> I pretend to Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</p>
            <p>But again, As to the innocency of Differences, why ſhould my Man be eſteemed a Criminal, or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41719:7"/>
as ſuch, whoſe Deſires and Intentions are to pleaſe his Maker as well as mine? We ſee all Rivers, little and great, at laſt diſcharge themſelves into the Ocean; and all Diviſions and Sects of Chriſtians have the ſame End and Tendency, and Terminate in the ſame Center, <hi>viz.</hi> in endeavouring to Pleaſe, to Glorifie and Honour their Maker. Why there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould the diſtinct Ways and Methods in Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, be more a Reproach than thoſe in Temporals; and Men not to be allowed to chooſe for themſelves their Method in obtaining a Manſion in another World, as well as ſecuring a Poſſeſſion in this? Their own Souls lies at ſtake, which if they have any appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of, muſt needs oblige them to be ſincere. But this interpoſing in other Mens Matters, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over-Officious, I like not; and they that force their own Inventions and Models of Worſhip on other Men, under the ſpecious pretences of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> do (I am afraid) <hi>force a Trade</hi> rather than Truth, which ſtands in need of no <hi>Coercion.</hi> And indeed there is ſuch a myſterious <hi>Trade</hi> driven in the Concerns of Religion, and ſo much Gain got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſome particular Methods, that 'tis no wonder Men <hi>contended ſo earneſtly</hi> for them.</p>
            <p>And amongſt other hindrances of true Hollneſs, and Chriſtian Affection, and of the Eſtabliſhment of Truth and Peace among us, are the <hi>Dignities, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> and <hi>large Revenues</hi> of <hi>Spiritual Men:</hi> And I beg ſome Gentlemens <hi>Pardon</hi> if I think amiſs, when I ſay I believe the <hi>Flames of Contention</hi> that are afoot, and ſo much diſturb Chriſtendom, would <hi>ceaſe</hi> and abate, were the Oily Subſtance of <hi>their fat Benefices</hi> a little diminiſhed or taken away: And that a great many Men would not think it worth their while to contend ſo about the <hi>inviſible</hi> things of <hi>another</hi> World, were there not a great deal to be gotten in <hi>this.</hi> But in order to a Concluſion:</p>
            <p>We may hope and wiſh Truth and Peace to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in the World, but we never ſhall ſee it, as long as Temporals are ſo mixt with Spirituals: There will never be a proſperous or bleſſed Iſſue of ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hallowed and unſanctified mixture. But when there is a <hi>Divorce</hi> put to <hi>theſe,</hi> and all Power of the Church be devolved on the State; and the Men be choſen in <hi>another manner,</hi> and their <hi>Allowances</hi> ſetled on them by the State; and when Learning is better ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged and reformed. For the Poet ſaith but too true,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Whatſoever ill the State invades,</l>
               <l>The Pulpit either forces or perſwades;</l>
               <l>Others may bring the Fewel to the Fire,</l>
               <l>But they the Breath which makes the Flame aſpire.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And that was but an unlucky ſort of Comment, which one made of thoſe Words wrote over the Head of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Saviour by <hi>Pilate,</hi> in <hi>Hebrew, Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> That he ſhould be perſeeuted moſt by men skilfull in thoſe Languages: For 'tis the Learned men are the Warriers, and manage all our Contentions; they would in a manner naturally Disband, had they not ſuch Leaders, who have little elſe to do but to raiſe unneceſſary Quarrels, and ſet the World together by the Ears. The other three parts of the World have <hi>little</hi> leaſure, and <hi>leſs</hi> will and abilities to maintain them; I ſay when Learning is better managed, and when a perfect and unalterable Toleration of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions in Religion is eſtabliſhed, then the Eternal God will bleſs the World with Truth and Peace; but 'tis only the laſt, I mean Toleration, which we at preſent may expect, and that for the Reaſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned; as alſo for the unvaluable Benefits here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after we ſhall certainly reap thereby. For in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,</p>
            <p>What can more contribute to the Security, Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Fouriſhing State of this Unhappy Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than by one joint and Univerſal Act, to Aboliſh all thoſe Grievances which have ſo long diſturbed our Peace? I mean <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Tests;</hi> and at the ſame time to Settle and Eſtabliſh a <hi>Great Pacifick Charter,</hi> that Hell it ſelf, nor all the United Force of Malicious Men ſhall never be able to diſturb: Wherein every one cannot fail to find their Account, except thoſe who are not fit to be quieted or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, becauſe they will not be ſatisfied with their proportion of Power, or good Livings, but demand all. But leaving ſuch unreaſonable men to be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged into Compliance, by that Power, which I hope will do it effectually, I promiſe my ſelf, that all the reſt will not betray ſo much Weakneſs, as not to acquieſce in ſuch a <hi>Sovereign Expedient,</hi> which will certainly redound to the good of the whole. For hereby every one will have his Religion ſecured to him, by as good a Title as his Land; every one will be ſecured from the Deſtructive and Fiery Zeal of his Violent Neighbour: And ſince <hi>humanum eſt errare,</hi> and Miſtakes and Errors will be, as long as there be men; yet this <hi>Great Charter</hi> will protect all from the evil of one anothers miſtakes; and will put an end to mens ruining and killing one another for God's ſake; will make the <hi>Lyon lie down with the Lamb, and ſilence the voice of Complaints in our Streets;</hi> will check the Inſolence and Ill Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Perverſe Men, of all ſides; and let men Worſhip their Maker ſincerely and truly, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Hypocriſie; will make His Majeſty's Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment eaſie, and prevent Factions, Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies againſt it; will give Him leave to exert His Royal Vertues, and make as conſiderable a Figure in Chriſtendom as any of His Anceſtors; will take
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41719:7"/>
away all the pretenſions ill men may have from Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercion and Reſtraint, and leave them inexcuſable if Turbulent and Unquiet; ſo that none dare endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to Patronize them, or mitigate their Condign Puniſhment: Will lay aſleep all Fears and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and quiet the Paſſions and Animoſities of men, or at leaſt make them Impotent and Uncapable of doing Hurt. And in fine, that by its Proviſions and Sanctions, will qualifie things ſo, that men'of all Perſwaſions ſhall have an equal Claim and Title to Religion, Property, and their Princes Favour: and that no publick Emoluments, no Office, Intereſt, Benefit, Favour or Preferment, ſhall be denied to any man, on the account of his Perſwaſion; but purely on ſome Notorious <hi>Wicked Incapacity.</hi> And further, by its <hi>Pacifick Nature</hi> will gradually effect, that the preſent odious malignity affixed to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing Names of Chriſtians, ſhall be mortified and made innocent; and to go under ſeveral diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Denominations, ſhall be no more a Reproach to them, than it is for Citizens to be free of ſeveral Companies; or Country-men to be called by the Name of the County they were born in. But in anſwer to ſome Objections.</p>
            <p>If it be alledged, <hi>That the Papiſts ought not to have the Benefit of Toleration, becauſe of their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs:</hi> To this I anſwer, The ſame Argument holds good againſt any Side or Party; for they have been <hi>all</hi> wicked by Turns, when in Power, and have been pretty even one with another; and ſo, I think, have the greateſt Reaſon to agree: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, if we ſtay, and will admit of no Religion to receive an Eſtabliſhment, till its Profeſſors have clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves of all <hi>Real</hi> Crimes, or <hi>pretended</hi> ones; I am afraid we ſhall have no Religion at all: For all Sides have been really to Blame, and really Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, though every Side endeavour to Extenuate their Guilt; but being Parties, muſt not be Judges in their own Caſe. Their denying their Faults, does not make them leſs guilty, though ſome men think ſo; and by an odd ſort of Inference, they reckon to make another man a Criminal, is to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Innocent. And the principal thing urged in their Diſcourſe is, To <hi>magnifie</hi> others Faults, and <hi>leſſen</hi> their own. And this humour is ſo Epidemical, I meet it almoſt every where; and if they can prove, or make out any way, the Perſwaſion of another to be <hi>abſurd</hi> or <hi>odd,</hi> they look upon themſelves to be very good Chriſtians; never conſidering how eaſie a thing it is to make any thing <hi>abſurd;</hi> nor what dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ways of Falſhood there are; in ſome of which 'tis ten to one, but they themſelves may Tread.</p>
            <p>But to come to a more ingenuous Confeſſion, and as an Indifferent Perſon to ſpeak the Truth, and give all Sides their due; I proteſt I cannot in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience vindicate any Parties proceedings. The <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> have Faults enough, and the World is Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to find out more; (not to mention the miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations and foul charges, which is inſeparable to diſputing Parties:) Nor are the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters innocent, but in many things muſt acknowledge they have ſadly miſcarried; eſpecially in thoſe late unhappy troubles, in the Reign of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Much leſs is the Church of <hi>England</hi> to be excuſed, who by their Severities and Preſſures of Government, gave but too great provocations to both; and their <hi>Furious Driving</hi> like <hi>Jehu,</hi> is the principal Cauſe of moſt of our Troubles. They were the occaſion of the <hi>Scots</hi> Rebelling, Arch-Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> impoſing the <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> upon them, (contrary to the Conſtitution of their Nation) and of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and late Rebellions, by laying ſuch Loads on <hi>Diſſenters, which they would not help to bear with the leaſt of their Fingers;</hi> but moſt of all to blame by eſtabliſhing <hi>Iniquity by Law;</hi> and after ſo much <hi>miſchief</hi> done thereby, yet <hi>vindicate</hi> the ſame Law ſtill, and by Conſequence their Wicked Proceedings. In Calm Fits and Sober Hours, they confeſs their former ill Treatment by <hi>Diſſenters</hi> has made them over-act themſelves of Late. And why will not they allow this to be a good Plea in the Mouths of others, who over-acted themſelves too in their <hi>late</hi> and <hi>former</hi> Outrages; reſenting too deeply and unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly their Ill Uſage and Oppreſſion? Tyranny and Oppreſſion is the Original and Source of moſt violent Outrages; and when-ever the Banks are pull'd down, the Current runs with the greateſt Impetuoſity.</p>
            <p>'Tis well known the <hi>Papists</hi> have had but miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Treatment in <hi>England,</hi> ever ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but eſpecially ſince Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s time; and 'tis known as well that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> have had little better: And no wonder therefore that they have plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and been troubleſome to them that have kept them <hi>under:</hi> and the Church of <hi>England</hi> too, when under Hatches by the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> were Plotters to bring themſelves (though they called it the <hi>King)</hi> in again: Indeed they have not had ſo many <hi>Temptations</hi> as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; for ſince the Reformation they have been moſtly Regent, and in the Sunſhine: I ſhall not further object againſt them. what their Enemies have obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; but ſay they begin to ſhew themſelves Men, and exactly like other Men too, they grow angry and diſcontented; ſometimes Threaten, ſometimes Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then Reflect, ſtart Jealouſies, and raiſe Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bears; and uſe all the little Shifts and Artifices which their reputed Enemies, in much worſe Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, formerly uſed; and then were objected to them as Crimes. So that in Concluſion, after all the noiſe and talk of Loyalty, and good Principles, by every Party, I find <hi>none</hi> of them good, but when they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41719:8"/>
are pleaſed (which they ſay the Devil is) and <hi>none</hi> much worſe than another, but when they are are <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here, I know, will come in an Objection, and that is, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Papiſts by their Principles are ſo for from thinking it a ſin to deſtroy their Innocent Neighbours, (which are</hi> Heret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cks<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>as they call them) that they think it matter of Merit and Duty ſo to do.</hi> Here is an Objection with a Witneſs.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Pudet haec opprobria nobis,</l>
               <l>Et dici potuiſſe, &amp; non potuiſſe refelli.</l>
            </q>
            <p>If this could be prov'd, (which I never yet ſaw) and if they clear not themſelves from this, and give the World ſatisfaction; I am ſo far from <hi>extenuating</hi> ſuch a wicked Principle, that I think what Oppoſition their <hi>Adverſaries</hi> have <hi>already,</hi> or hereafter <hi>may</hi> make againſt them, is all but <hi>too little;</hi> and I think it my Duty, and ought to be the Duty of every Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew Man, to extirpate ſuch a Race of Men from the face of the Earth; and to reſpect them as a ſort of wild Beaſts, that would devour and Prey upon Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. God forbid I ſhould argue fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſuch a ſort of Men. What I argue for, is only for an Indulgence of Thought in things of an indifferent Nature, and Principles which terminate in Speculation, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <hi>no wicked Action.</hi> And I <hi>here</hi> declare again, as at firſt, That 'tis an unreaſonable thing, that any ſort of Men, under what Denomination ſoever, ſhould have the <hi>benefit</hi> of any Government, much leſs be admitted as a Member, or Adminiſtrator in it, un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs he do his endeavour to <hi>Encourage</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect</hi> it, and give Security for his quiet and peaceable Living under it.</p>
            <p>But then as our Saviour commended the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust Steward,</hi> ſo I cannot but commend all our Parties, and muſt needs ſay <hi>They do wiſely in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> abating their Honeſty and Integrity. For to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Church of <hi>England;</hi> Her Sons Act as Prudently as can be imagined; for they have got all into the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> own hands, all the Spiritual Preferments in the Nation; if <hi>any</hi> of them ſhould turn <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that is madneſs, for they have got <hi>all</hi> already; and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have <hi>nothing</hi> to give them: <hi>They</hi> know, that if either they move to the Right Hand, or the Left, they ſhall be <hi>Leſſened,</hi> ſince they are craving needy People on both S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des them: Therefore <hi>their Intereſt</hi> conſiſts in being obſtinate, and ſtanding out againſt the Kings Demands: They may be made <hi>leſs,</hi> but cannot be made <hi>greater:</hi> Therefore by all means poſſible they endeavour to keep thoſe under that would come in Snacks with them; alſo on the ſcore of their Abuſe, for they are Conſcious of the Injury they have done, and are afraid of <hi>Retaliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then as they cannot be blamed to keep their Wealth and Power; ſo on the other hand the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of others muſt not be blamed in getting what they can: And, who in Conſcience or Equity can <hi>accuſe</hi> them, who being Poor, Indigent, and ready to be Starved, do endeavour to ſupply their Wants, and come in Partners with the Poſſeſſors? 'Tis natural for every Man that has been Oppreſſed, to rid himſelf of his Yoke, and endeavour to ſecure himſelf for the future; and that Man deſerves to be hang'd, who ſtanding condemn'd by an unjuſt Law, and gets a Reprieve, will not endeavour to get ſo unjuſt a Law to be Repealed. But then the Injuſtice of the firſt, or the irregularity of the Methods of the Laſt, I cannot conſent to commend. And it grieves me to conſider, how <hi>Religion</hi> is made a Stalking-Horſe; and is taken up for a Pretence and Cloak to cover Mens baſe Deſigns; and indeed as far as ever I could obſerve, <hi>two thirds</hi> of that which Men call by that <hi>venerable Name,</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>Trick</hi> to get Money. And the Holy Scriptures are like Original Deeds, by which any Man that has but a little more Wit than Honeſty, may lay claim to an Eccleſiaſtical Poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But leaſt I ſhould be thought to ſpeak irreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thoſe Holy Books, I acknowledge, That if a man be ſincere and honeſt, and look for Truth as if he had a mind to find it; and have no other ends in his Search, but to pleaſe his Maker and ſave his Soul; he may eaſily find enough to make him both happy <hi>here</hi> and <hi>hereafter.</hi> But as far as I can ſee, men ſeem to underſtand moſt of the Scriptures backward. For whereas the Prophet ſaith, <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O Man, what the Lord requireth of thee, to do Juſtice, and love Mercy, and to walk Humbly with thy God.</hi> And the Apoſtle tells them, <hi>That True Religion before God and the Father, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in viſiting the Fatherleſs and Widows in their Affliction, and to keep themſelves unſpotted from the World;</hi> alſo another, <hi>That they ſhould follow Peace with all men, and Holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord:</hi> By their Actions and Living, they ſeem to underſtand them clear contrary; as if it had been ſaid thus, <hi>He hath ſhewed thee, O man, what the Lord requireth of thee, to do Injuſtice, to love Perſecution, and to walk at Enmity and Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with thy God.</hi> True Religion before God and the Father is this, <hi>To neglect the Fatherleſs, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict the Widows, and to conform themſelves to the Faſhions of the World; and follow Contention and Strife with all men, without which no man ſhall go to Heaven.</hi> Truely men's Actions ſeems to favour this latter Interpretation, rather than the former. And many other places of Scripture I could quote, which exhort to Love and Peace, and mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41719:8"/>
which men either do not, or will not underſtand; and 'tis a deplorable thing to conſider how <hi>partial</hi> they are in underſtanding the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Some Texts are great <hi>Favourites,</hi> when they ſeem to countenance their Intereſt or Deſigns; and others that will not <hi>Vote</hi> for them, are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhier'd, and a hundred Objections raiſed againſt them. That of <hi>Contend earneſtly for the Faith once delivered to the Saints,</hi> I warrant you at <hi>this time o'th' Day</hi> is a precious one; for here peeviſh Nature is gratified, and here if I have a mind to keep any thing that is <hi>dear</hi> to me, I have a Cover for my Diſh; 'tis but calling my Faction, my Paſſion, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, Prejudice, Intereſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the Venerable Name of True Faith; and then I have a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to contend earneſtly for it. <hi>Contend earneſtly with us for our Livings and Benefices, once delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us by the Laws,</hi> would not look well; <hi>But Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend earneſtly for the Faith,</hi> that's plauſible and goes down glib. I will readily allow the Objection which I ſee is ready to come upon me, that is, <hi>That men are obliged in Conſcience to contend for the Faith, or that which they think to be true;</hi> yet this <hi>Contention</hi> ought not to proceed further than to <hi>Edification;</hi> and if any other Methods be uſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides <hi>calm Reaſoning</hi> and <hi>Argument,</hi> that deſtroy Charity, an <hi>Indifference</hi> is better than ſuch Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And when men exhort their Auditory to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions;</hi> however innocent their Meaning and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions may be, yet their Diſcretion muſt be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and they will never be able to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of publick Cenſure, if they do not qualifie their Diſcourſe with all the Limitations and Reſtrictions imaginable; for men are too apt to <hi>Contend</hi> without Exhortation.</p>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>But to Conclude,</head>
               <p>SINCE in ſo many Ages, no Humane Art or Induſtry, nor all the Powers on Earth together, by either Force or Stratagem, neither hitherto have found, nor hereafter can poſſibly find an Expedient, or make it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, amidſt ſo many various and all incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent <hi>Mediums,</hi> That all men ſhould be of one Mind, or that they ſhould not Diſagree, not be Deceived, or not have Differences and Contentions; I ſay, ſince theſe things are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be done, <hi>(Salva veritate,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Liberty of Judgment) the Attempt is Vain and Fooliſh, and not to be proſecuted but by Fools or Mad Men. And ſince it is ſo, the next thing which naturally comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſideration is, How to make all things as Innocent and Eaſie, and Suitable to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as poſſible. All which things His Gracius Majeſty having duly Weighed and Conſidered; out of Great Experience, Deep Wiſdom, and Princely Compaſſion towards His miſerable contending Subjects, hath found out and pitched upon the only Expedient in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereto. I mean a <hi>Great Pacifick Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> which though it cannot ſubdue mens Ill Nature and Will, yet will put it out of the Power of any one Contending Party to hurt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. 'Tis this Inſtrument and only this, (with God's Bleſſing) can make our miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Contending Nation Happy. And he either does not truly underſtand his Intereſt, or is no True <hi>Engliſh-Man,</hi> who doth not heartily deſire it, and by all honeſt means endeavour to promote it. And I doubt not, maugre all the Oppoſition of Intereſted and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable Men, but that His Majesty will duly Effect it. The Almighty, all Good and Wiſe God, who put it in his Heart, no doubt but will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him in it; and if ſo, <hi>Gamaliel's</hi> Advice is pertinent in the Caſe, <hi>To ſtrive againſt the Almighty, will be to no purpoſe;</hi> They but in vain promiſe themſelves ſucceſs, againſt the <hi>King of Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> It ſeems to be an Honour and a Bleſſing reſerved by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on purpoſe for him; and is an Action and Performance truly worthy of ſo Judicious, ſo Just, &amp; ſo Couragious a Prince; and will raiſe Him a Name, and a Monument, not to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced by the Spight of Time, or Succeſſion of Ages.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for the Author. 1688.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
